<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ libraries for rapid development of cross-platform financial WEB-applications.</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Why should you choose Beigesoft™ software (libraries).">

    <p>
      First, an application based on Beigesoft™ libraries works anywhere. The all parts - ORM, PDF Writer (reporting tool), WEB-interface work on standard Java as well as on Android one.
    </p>
    <p>
      Second, they are fast. The all parts work fast even on weak devices such as a smartphone. Beige WEB interface is based on JSP. JSP WEB-view technology is the same as PHP, ASPX, etc. This is the dominant WEB-view technology (mostly used).
      JSP is faster than PHP (and other script languages) because of compiling JSP-bytecode into processor code on time (Just In Time bytecode compiler). The Beige-PDF writer caches TTF fonts and makes PDF files with only used characters, so you will never get a huge PDF file or wait a long time for it.
      Standard ORMs use "lazy initialization" to retrieve entity's fields. That means that they use several SQL queries to retrieve whole model.
      Beige ORM retrieves the whole model by using only(single) SQL query (with JOINS). A one big SQL query (exactly with JOINS) that retrieves all data is always faster then several small SQL queries that retrieve the same data.
    </p>
    <p>
      Third, with these libraries you are able to build very complex business applications quickly. You can check it by yourself by making the example application in the next articles.
      Beige PDF writer can't make charts or barcodes. It took me 3 months to program Beige PDF. PDF is naturally able to draw lines and shapes. It will not be long or difficult to implement a chart or a bar-code. And this is a regular task even for an IT student.
      Programming a report without a visual editor is actually a reliable and quick way.
    </p>
    <p>
      Fourth, they and all 3-party software are under truly free licenses. BSD 2-Clause License means:
      <ul>
        <li>it's open source (you can modify it)</li>
        <li>it's free for any purposes (even for commercial purposes)</li>
        <li>there is no any warranty</li>
        <li>there is no any liability</li>
        <li>you must include copyright in any redistribution of these libraries (software that use Beigesoft libraries), e.g. just make a regular HTML page that lists all the parts and their licenses (in the way that's similar to a book)</li>
        <li>these terms are forever</li>
      </ul>
      They blame that this license is advertising. Have you ever seen a reliable book without reference page? Omitting of used sources in a book is lawless.
      And it's not about advertising, it's about "the authors", "the terms" and "the author's responsibilities". There are a lot of useless software (especially duplicates) that just dedicated to waste your time.
      The last time when the Law hits such ugly things in the IT sphere was the "data privacy". Many business owners bore direct losses because of it, for example imposing additional fees to prevent publishing WHOIS information.
      In other hand, there are software with "non-proper" or "unclear" licenses and authors. Just take a look inside an open-source software, and you might find a part with a non-free or unclear license.
    </p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
