<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Enterprise Information System</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Overseas sales. Advanced internationalization.">
      
      <p>Keywords: overseas sales.</p>

      <h4>Overseas sales. Advanced internationalization.</h4>
      <p>Nowadays international trading is still growing sphere of business.
        Even small business entities do overseas sales (export) or import.</p>
      <p>Overseas buyer usually have not to pay foreign sales taxes. For example, foreigners travelers can refund sales taxes when they leave the country.
        You should set "Omit taxes" in any invoice for such customers/vendors.
      </p>
      <p>Foreign buyers that buy goods for business purpose (e.g. for resale) usually must have a translated invoice. This is required by their tax authority.
        Beigesoft™ EIS has advanced dynamic internationalization to do it. This helps foreigner buyers and might attract more of them.
      </p>
      <h4>Making sales invoice translated in buyer's native language.</h4>
      <p>
        At first add foreign buyer, e.g. "OOO Berezka" from Russia, then add Buyer internationalization for this buyer in Russian language:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/forgnbuyerru.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Then add Internationalization base business owner information in Russian language:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/bownerru.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Then add goods/service/unit of measure internationalization in Russian language:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/goodsru.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Then add currency internationalization USD in Russian language:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/currencyru.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>* after changing internalization things such as currency or base, you should restart application.</p>
      <p>
        Finally just add invoice, its report in English is:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/foregninvrepen.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Set Russian language, digit separator "comma" and group separator "space" in "Change language preferences":
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/langprefch.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Then print invoice again in Russian:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/foregninvrepru.png" /></p>
      </p>

      <h4>How to add new language without recompiling.</h4>
      <p>Beigesoft™ EIS uses TTF fonts DejaVuSerif-Bold.ttf and DejaVuSerif.ttf that contain many languages. For other languages you should add TTF file into Java archive file (see below).
        Asian free TTF fonts you can find:
        <ul>
          <li>Japanese VL-Gothic fonts - <a href="http://vlgothic.dicey.org">http://vlgothic.dicey.org</a></li>
          <li>Korean Nanum fonts - <a href="https://slackbuilds.org/repository/14.0/system/nanum-fonts-ttf/">https://slackbuilds.org/repository/14.0/system/nanum-fonts-ttf/</a></li>
          <li>Chinese Han Sans - <a href="https://github.com/be5invis/source-han-sans-ttf/releases">https://github.com/be5invis/source-han-sans-ttf/releases</a></li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>Java files are placed in JAR file, that is actually a ZIP archive. JAR, WAR and APK are ZIP archives. All you should do is:
        <ul>
          <li>extract files with folders (tree structure) into folder e.g. "foo"</li>
          <li>add basic static internationalization - file e.g. /resources/Messages_fr_FR.properties for France language, just copy file Messages_en_US.properties to Messages_fr_FR-UTF8.properties, edit it in UTF-8 editor, encode it to ASCII by command <b>native2ascii -encoding UTF-8 Messages_fr_FR-UTF8.properties Messages_fr_FR.properties</b>.</li>
          <li>add language and country codes into <b>langCountries</b> in <b>web.xml</b>, e.g. <b>en,US,ru,RU,fr,FR</b></li>
          <li>remove digital signatures - foo/META-INF/BEIGESOF.RSA and BEIGESOF.SF</li>
          <li>if need, add new TTF fonts into <b>fonts</b> folder</li>
          <li>make JAR/WAR file by <b>jar</b> utility, e.g. run outside of "foo" folder: "jar cvfm beige-eis.jar foo/META-INF/MANIFEST.MF -C foo/ ."</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>At first, add new language, country and language preferences, then push "refresh languages settings", then refresh page. Then add goods, service, etc. names in new language.</p>
      <p>To use another TTF file, set it name without extension in "Accounting settings"-"TTF font",
        for example "VL-Gothic-Regular" (if there is no another Bold TTF, then leave that field "TTF font bold" empty!). <a href="files/invoice-jp.pdf">Example of partially internationalized invoice with "VL-Gothic-Regular.ttf"</a>
      </p>
      <p>If you set "Accounting settings"-"page size" to "Letter", then you have to set page margins and font size in inches, otherwise (default A4) is millimeters. Default font size 3.5 millimeters equals to 0.1378 inch.</p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
