<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Enterprise Information System</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of purchase, prepayments, payments tracking, bank reconciliation.">

      <p>Keywords: Accounting of purchase, prepayments, sales taxes from purchase, payments tracking, bank reconciliation.</p>

      <h4>Sales taxes that is payed on a purchase of raw materials (producing USA).</h4>
      <p>According <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p535.pdf">IRS 535 Business Expenses, Page 18</a> sales taxes that Bob pays on purchase of materials
      are business expenses (sales taxes are included into material cost),  i.e. they are deducting income tax:
<pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
...
Any sales tax you pay on a service for your business, or on the purchase or use of property
in your business is treated as part of the cost of the service or property.
If the service or the cost or use of the property is a deductible business expense,
you can deduct the tax as part of that service or cost.
If the property is merchandise bought for resale, the sales tax is part of the cost of the merchandise.
...
</pre>  
        That is sales taxes from purchase is included into inventory and they become expenses automatically as part of Cost Of Goods Sold (method FIFO in this case).
        So Bob should set accounting settings "Extract sales taxes from purchase" to No,
        and set "Enabled" to No for "Entries source" #4 "Purchase invoice. Debit Sales tax from purchase per tax, Credit Payable per vendor for tax amount.":
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS settings - sales taxes from purchase" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/entrsourcestfrpur.png" /></p>
        Also he should set "Enabled" to No asset account <b>Sales Tax From Purchase</b>.
      </p>
      <p>
        If you have to use different method to account sales tax from purchase,
        then set accounting settings "Extract sales taxes from purchase" to Yes,
        and set "Enabled" to Yes for method #4 "Purchase invoice. Debit Sales tax from purchase per tax, Credit Payable per vendor for tax amount."
        Then you should set "Enabled" to true asset account <b>Sales Tax From Purchase</b>. Also you should add sales taxes, item tax categories and set tax category for goods/service (see <a href="eis-selling.html">Accounting of sales, prepayments, payments tracking.</a>)
        You are able to change tax amount in a purchase invoice line (item basis and aggregate/only rate) or total invoice (invoice basis).
        In USA extracting taxes from purchase (from item's cost) is required in case of using "inventory capitalized costs" method (see <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p538.pdf">IRS 538, Page 18 Uniform Capitalization Rules</a>).
        Capitalized cost becomes an expense partially, depending on ending inventory (final product).
      </p>
      <p>For many other countries sales taxes (e.g. VAT, GST) from purchases are always extracted from goods/service cost, and they deduct themselves (taxes from purchases deduct taxes from sales).</p>
      
      <h4>Prepayments</h4>
      <p>Bob prepaid goods to Carlo's grocery on 14 Jan:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS prepayment for purchase" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/prepforpurc.png" /></p>
          * field <b>Total FC</b> is used in case of purchases made in foreign currency.
      </p>
      <p>"Prepayment for purchase" has made simple accounting entries:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS prepayment for purchase report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/prepforpurcrep.png" /></p>
      </p>

      <p>
        * After a document is accounted (made entries) you can't change it, you can only reverse it
        or change description (only) of its accounting entries. Beigesoft™ EIS is designed for high load job,
        this kind of software requires accuracy, otherwise you will get mess-up quickly. Just make database backup more frequently.
      </p>
      
      <h4>Purchase</h4>
      <p>
        Bob bought pizza ingredients on Jan 15, then filled purchase invoice, then accounted it:
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS purchase invoice" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase1.png" /></p>
        <p>Field <b>pay by date</b> is optional, fields <b>Foreign currency</b> and <b>exchange rate</b> are used for purchases in foreign currency, after you added invoice line in native currency they will disappear.</p>
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS purchase invoice report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase11.png" /></p>
        <p align="center">full report  is:</p>
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS purchase invoice report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase1r.png" /></p>
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS purchase invoice report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/purchase1r1.png" /></p>
        <p>* As you can see, purchase invoice makes automatically accounting record prepayments to account payable. Only prepayment per invoice is allowed (implemented),
        otherwise you should make prepayments and payments tracking "by hand".</p>
        <p>* You also can see that sales tax for cheese is included into its cost, i.e. it is not extracted.</p>
      </p>

      <h4>Payments tracking</h4>
      <p>Bob paid the rest to Carlo's grocery for purchase invoice#1 on 15 Jan:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS payment for purchase" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/paypurch.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>Document "Payment for purchase" made simple accounting entries:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS payment for purchase report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/paypurchrep.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>Purchase invoice's payment's tracking fields in the list are changed after that:
          <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS payment for purchase tracking" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/paypurchtrack.png" /></p>
      </p>

      <h4>Bank reconciliation</h4>
      <p>When bank account balance in your accounting system (software or book) is not same as in the bank (in the bank statement),
        then you have to make adjusting entries. This is called "bank reconciliation".
        For example, yesterday you received a check for 500USD from customer "Firm A" and made this accounting entry:
        <pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
Debit CashInBank.Account#243443354 for 500USD Credit AccountsReceivable.FirmA for 500USD
        </pre>
        After that your bank account balance is 10000USD (in your accounting system).
        Today you received the bank statement that is saying that the check was rejected, and you was charged for 10USD additionally cause that "wrong check",
        and the balance is 9490USD.
        So you have to make two adjusting entries:
        <pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
Credit CashInBank.Account#243443354 for 500USD Debit AccountsReceivable.FirmA for 500USD
Credit CashInBank.Account#243443354 for 10USD Debit Expenses.BankExpenses for 10USD
        </pre>
      </p>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
