<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Enterprise Information System.</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Destination-based sales tax. Overriding vendor's tax calculation method.">
      
      <p>Keywords: destination-based vs origin-based sales tax.</p>
      
      <h4>Destination-based sales tax. Overriding vendor's tax calculation method.</h4>
      <p>If law of your country allows to use different sales tax calculation methods, then you can set <b>Tax destination</b> method for vendors with different methods.
        For example you use HALF-UP rounding and item basis method, but a vendor uses HALF-DOWN and invoice basis,
        then just create <b>Tax destination</b> with different methods and set it in this vendor.
        You are also able to change sales tax amount in invoice line (item basis) or in invoice total (invoice basis).
      </p>
      <p>If sales taxes in your country depend of a region (state, province, county, etc., e.g. this applies in USA), then
      you should add <b>Tax destination</b> for that region and set it in customers (from that region),
      then add <b>Item tax category</b> with destination sales taxes,
      then add <b>Tax destination line</b> (tax destination-destination tax category) for selling items.
      When you sell such items to "other destination customers", then "destination taxes" will be used instead of <b>tax category of item (origin taxes)</b>.</p>
      
      <h4>Example of destination-based sales tax.</h4>
      <p>Assume, Bob has sold same items to two customers - <b>Mini-mart</b> from New York, <b>FSC</b> from other state.
        Taxable items in NY (aggregate rate, item basis, half-up):
        <ul>
          <li>Cheese, STG4.7%, STG6.4%</li>
          <li>Armchair, STG4.7%, STG6.4%</li>
          <li>Sofa, STG4.7%, STG6.4%</li>
          <li>Delivering, STS11%</li>
        </ul>
        Taxable items in other state (aggregate rate, invoice basis, half-down):
        <ul>
          <li>Cheese, STF2.7%, STF3.17%, STF1.234%</li>
          <li>Armchair, non taxable</li>
          <li>Sofa, origin taxable</li>
          <li>Delivering, STF11%</li>
        </ul>
        Price inclusive of taxes for both cases.
      </p>
      <p>
        After adding foreign state sales taxes and category, add foreign state tax destination:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satadest1.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Then set foreign state tax destination in the customer FSC:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satadest2.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>
        Then set foreign state tax destination and taxes "STF2.7%, STF3.17%, STF1.234%" in the merchandise "Cheese":
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satadest3.png" /></p>
        * Delivering is made in the same way.
      </p>
      <p>
        Then set foreign state tax destination and empty tax category in the product "Armchair" to make it non-taxable in "other state":
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satadest4.png" /></p>
      </p>
      <p>To make item "origin-bases" taxable in other state do nothing (this is about "Sofa").</p>
      <p>
        Finally, make two invoices to local (Mini-mart) and foreign (FSC) state customers with the same items and prices:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satadest5.png" /></p>
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satadest6.png" /></p>
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satadest7.png" /></p>
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satadest8.png" /></p>
      </p>
      
      <h4>Omit taxes in invoice</h4>
      <p>In case if customer bought merchandise for resale, sales taxes may be omitted (this applies in USA for example), so just set "omit taxes" to "yes" in such invoice.</p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
