<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Enterprise Information System</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of sales taxes cash method, cash method vs accrual method.">

    <p>Keywords: Accounting of sales taxes cash method, cash method vs accrual method.</p>

    <h4>Basic principles.</h4>
    <p>At first, it's need to understand these things:
      <ul>
        <li>Prepaid merchandise - means that buyer has paid 100% for this merchandise and has not yet received it (merchandise).</li>
        <li>Paid merchandise - means that buyer has paid/prepaid 100% for this merchandise and has received it (merchandise).</li>
        <li>Prepaid/paid partially - means that buyer has paid less then 100% for this merchandise.</li>
        <li>Sold merchandise - means that buyer has received this merchandise*.</li>
      </ul>
      *for some countries term "sold" may means also "the merchandise is sent to the buyer". In Beigesoft™ EIS "sold/bought" means when an invoice is accounted (document has made accounting entries).
    </p>
    <p>Accrual or cash method is dedicated to making income tax "WHEN" (all other taxes usually have the same method as income tax).</p>
    <p>The most used method for income tax is:
    <pre style="white-space:pre-wrap">
      Income tax = (Business revenue - Business expenses) * Tax Rate
    </pre>
    There are two methods "WHEN" revenue or expense is occurred:
    <ul>
      <li>CASH method - means that expense/revenue/tax is occurred when merchandise is sold and paid.</li>
      <li>ACCRUAL method - means that expense/revenue/tax is occurred when merchandise is sold (even unpaid or partially paid).</li>
    </ul>
    Cash method is used in tax accounting only in simple cases - when income is low.
    Accrual is only reliable method to properly estimate business results and it is used in market (financial) accounting.
    If you have choice between these methods for tax accounting, then you should better opt accrual method.
    </p>
    
    <h4>Sales taxes cash method</h4>
    <p>In some countries the law may demand to use cash method for sales taxes despite of using accrual method for income tax.</p>
    <p>In Beigesoft™ EIS you can use this method for sales, purchases and their returns.</p>
    <p>Lets make a purchase for example. At first, set enabled of "Entries sources":
      <ul>
        <li><b>Sales taxes methods must be switched according to current rules (here is: Cash=On, Accrual=Off)</b></li>
        <li><b>Sales:</b></li>
        <li>#27 "Payment from. Debit Receivable per customer, Credit Sales taxes payable per tax for tax amount, when Payments>=Sales, CASH!!!" set on.</li>
        <li>#26 "Sales invoice. Debit Receivable per customer, Credit Sales taxes payable per tax for tax amount, when Payments>=Sales, CASH!!!" set on.</li>
        <li>#11 "Sales invoice. Debit Receivable per customer, Credit Sales taxes payable per tax for tax amount." set off.</li>
        <li>#30 "Sales return. Debit Sales tax receivable from returns per Tax, Credit Returns Payable per Customer for tax amount, when Payments+Returns>=Sales, CASH!!!" set on.</li>
        <li>#17 "Sales return. Debit Sales tax receivable from returns per Tax, Credit Returns Payable per Customer for tax amount." set off.</li>
        <li><b>Purchases:</b></li>
        <li>#29 "Payment to. Debit Sales tax from purchase per tax, Credit Payable per vendor for tax amount, when Payments>=Purchases, CASH!!!" set on.</li>
        <li>#28 "Purchase invoice. Debit Sales tax from purchase per tax, Credit Payable per vendor for tax amount, when Payments>=Purchases, CASH!!!" set on.</li>
        <li>#4 "Purchase invoice. Debit Sales tax from purchase per tax, Credit Payable per vendor for tax amount." set off.</li>
        <li>#31 "Purchase return. Debit Returns Receivable per vendor, Credit Sales Tax Payable from returns per Tax for tax amount, when Payments+Returns>=Purchases, CASH!!!" set on.</li>
        <li>#15 "Purchase return. Debit Returns Receivable per vendor, Credit Sales Tax Payable from returns per Tax for tax amount." set off.</li>
      </ul>
      Also set in accounting settings "Extract sales taxes from sales" to "ON". Example of switching entries source, e.g.:
        <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/entrsour.png" /></p>
    </p>
    <h4>100% prepaid invoice.</h4>
    <p>Add 100% prepayments to vendor (13 Jul. 2016, 668.54$ total) and to account it.
      Then add sales invoice (14 Jul. 2016, 668.54$ total) with that prepayment:
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satacashinv1.png" /></p>
    </p>
    <p>After invoice has been accounted, the report is:
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satacashinv2.png" /></p>
      As you can see it made all accounting entries: taxes, receivable to revenue, inventory to COGS, adjusting prepayments to receivable.
    </p>
    <h4>50% prepaid invoice plus 25%*2 payments.</h4>
    <p>Add 50% prepayments to vendor (15 Jul. 2016, 334.27$ total) and to account it.
      Then add sales invoice with the same goods and services as above one (17 Jul. 2016, 668.54$ total),
      then to account it, the report is:
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satacashinv3.png" /></p>
      As you can see it made not all accounting entries: receivable to revenue, inventory to COGS, adjusting prepayments to receivable.
    </p>
    <p>Then add payment (18 Jul. 2016, 167.14$ total) and account it:
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satacashpay1.png" /></p>
      As you can see it made only cash to receivable accounting entries.
    </p>
    <p>Then add the rest payment (19 Jul. 2016, 167.13$ total) and account it:
      <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/satacashpay2.png" /></p>
      As you can see it made cash to receivable and taxes to receivable accounting entries.
    </p>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
