<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Enterprise Information System</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of employment (payroll).">
      
      <p>Keywords: Accounting of employment (payroll).</p>
      
<p>Beigesoft™ EIS has implemented widely used in many countries <b>tax table percentage method</b> for automatically calculation wage taxes.</p>
<p>It has implemented automatically calculation <b>wage tax = tax percent (according tables) * (gross wage - all allowances per payment)</b>. This simple method is used in USA.
In others countries it's used little more complex method <b>allowances per year</b>, which application hasn't implemented automatically yet.
</p>
<p>
  Bob has hired Rob Swallow as a cook.
  He filled out Employee category, Employee and Wage Types for Rob:
  <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS wage" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/employee.png" /></p>
  * use TIN (SSN) or phone number for emmployee ID. At least use IDs that have same number of digits, e.g. 6 digits ID from 100000 to 999999.
  This is because of using this parent ID for its automatic lines (year wage), e.g. Employee ID 100000 has two lines year wage with ID 1000001 and 1000002.
  <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS wage" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wagty.png" /></p>
  Bob uses <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p15.pdf">IRS Publication 15</a> (<b>IRS-ETG</b>) to account employment federal taxes, and
  <a href="https://www.tax.ny.gov/pdf/publications/withholding/nys50_t_nys.pdf">NYS New York State Withholding Tax</a> for state ones.
  So he filled out wage tax tables.
</p>
  <p>
    1. Federal Income Tax from employee wage.
    Rob filled form W-4 and got two withholding allowances. Bob elected percentage method, so according Table 5 (page 42 of <b>IRS-ETG</b>)
    allowance daily is 15.6 * 2 = 31.2. Bob should use table 8 (page 45 of <b>IRS-ETG</b>) to withhold Federal Income tax,
    so he has filled Employment -  Wage tax table according it:
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS tax percentage method" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wttfit.png" /></p>
          * any tax table line requires entering manually ID, so use simple formula:
<pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
  1000 + TAX TABLE ID append LINE INDEX, e.g. here first line should be 1000 + 1 append 1 = 10011, and second = 10012 end so on.
</pre>
    Here 1000 gives you ability to have up to 8999 different tax tables with ID from 1-8999 without their lines ID collisions.
    First and 123 line's ID of TT:
<pre style="white-space: pre-wrap;">
  TT ID LINE#1 ID LINE#123 ID 
  1     10011      1001123
  199   11991      1199123
  1100  21001      2100123
  5155  61551      6155123
  8999  99991      9999123
</pre>
* as you can see different entities, e.g. lines of different types in this case, can have the same ID.
  </p>
  <p>
    2. Medicare Tax from employee wage.
    According <b>IRS-ETG</b> its rate is 1.45%, so he has filled new Wage tax table:
    <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wttmt.png" /></p>
  </p>
  <p>
    3. Social Security Tax from employee wage.
    According <b>IRS-ETG</b> its rate is 6.2% with year wage limit 118500 USD,
    he has filled SST Wage tax table:
    <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wttsst.png" /></p>
  </p>
  <p>
    4. Federal Unemployment Tax from EMPLOYER. According <b>IRS-ETG</b> its rate is 6% with year wage limit 7000 USD,
    so he has filled FUTA Wage tax table:
    <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wttfuta.png" /></p>
    * make sure that you set the tax type properly (from employee or employer).
  </p>
  <p>
    5. New York Income Tax from employee wage.
    According <a href="https://www.tax.ny.gov/pdf/publications/withholding/nys50_t_nys.pdf">NYS New York State Withholding Tax</a>
    Rob's two allowances by form W-4 give him daily allowance 36.15 (Table-A on page 14). Bob uses table II-E (page 17)
    to figure NY Income tax, so he has filled NY Income Wage tax table according it:
    <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wttnit.png" /></p>
  </p>
  <p>
    Rob made on Jan 17 12 Pizza with bacon Frozen and 12 Pizza with cheese Frozen, then delivered them to customers.
    Bob has filled Wage document for 60 USD gross for cooking
    and 20 USD for delivering. He set tax account expense to <b>5105 Expenses</b>,
    then pressed <b>save</b>, then added wage line for cooking (account <b>Inventory direct cost temporary</b> for direct labor cost),
    and line for delivering (<b>5105 Expenses</b> for indirect labor cost):
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS payroll" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wageld.png" /></p>
    <p>then pressed button <b>fill taxes</b>, then accounted document:</p>
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS payroll" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wage1.png" /></p>
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS payroll report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/wage2.png" /></p>
    <p>
      As you can see cooking(direct labor) wage is accounted separately from delivery(indirect labor) one.
      For manufacturing direct labor cost (as well as cost of materials) is usually included into cost of the final product.
      Make sure that it's true for your tax rules.
    </p>
  </p>
<p>
  I guess that you noticed that Bob made mistake, he forget about NY unemployment tax (<a href="https://labor.ny.gov/ui/employerinfo/quarterly-reporting.shtm">NY SUTA requirements and limit</a>
  <a href="https://labor.ny.gov/ui/bpta/contribution-rates.shtm">NY SUTA rate</a>
  <a href="https://www.tax.ny.gov/pdf/publications/withholding/nys50.pdf">NY SUTA instructions.</a>).
  So you should make sure that you made all properly according the law of your country. Tax authorities provide full information with examples on its Internet site.
  You should study it thoroughly, if you have a question, then call to your tax authority and ask them.
  Otherwise if you made mistake, then you will get penalty, e.g. if you deduct your income tax with wrong cost of goods sold (deducting expense is greater than you can prove).
  You have to make (and keep) records that shows these properly calculations according <a href="https://www.irs.gov/pub/irs-pdf/p583.pdf">IRS 583 Starting a business, page 12</a>.
  Beigesoft™ EIS respect this, in addition it makes many records automatically (COGS, employment taxes, sales taxes, etc.)
  and reports to prove your business expenses.
</p>

<p>
  Trial balance after that is:
    <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS payroll balance" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/balanemp.png" /></p>
</p>
<h4>Allowance per year</h4>
<p>
  To use more complex method <b>allowances per year</b> don't fill allowances in tax tables. Fill taxes automatically, then  change allowances in wage tax lines and taxes in wage lines by hand.
  For example Jim Gold got 2000 EUR allowances per year for Income tax 12%. He is paid 1500 EUR per month, so tax lines will be:
  <ul>
    <li>1st month - allowance used 1500 (the rest 500) - no tax</li>
    <li>2nd month - allowance used 500 (the rest 0) - tax = (1500-500)*0.12</li>
    <li>3d, 4th ... months - allowance is 0, so tax = 1500*0.12</li>
  </ul>
</p>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
