<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ Enterprise Information System</title>
   </properties>

  <body>

    <section name="Accounting of manufacturing (producing).">

<p>Keywords: Accounting of manufacturing, direct and indirect labor, cost of product.</p>

      <p>Beigesoft™ EIS automatically calculates <b>cost of product = cost of materials
       plus additional costs (direct labor, packaging etc)</b>. This method is widely used in many countries.</p>
      <p>
        Rob made on Jan 17 12 Pizza with bacon frozen and 12 Pizza with cheese frozen. There are two documents for manufacturing:
        <ul>
          <li>Manufacturing process that makes a <b>product in progress</b> by using materials and usually direct labor cost, and makes accounting, draw material and warehouse entries (warehouse receipt/issue)</li>
          <li>Manufacture. It just transfers completed <b>product in progress</b> into <b>finished product</b>, and makes accounting, draw material and warehouse entries</li>
        </ul>
        Bob filled manufacturing process for 12 Pizza with cheese frozen:
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS manufacturing" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manufprc1.png" /></p>
        <p>Bob added one half of direct labor cost 45.91 (22.95) from Inventory capitalized cost temporary according (see Wage full report).
        After completing and accounting its full report is:</p>
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS manufacturing report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manufprc2.png" /></p>
        <p align="center"><img alt="Beigesoft™ EIS manufacturing report" style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manufprc2-1.png" /></p>
        <p>
          Then Bob filled and accounted Manufacture based on Manufacturing process above:
          <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manuf1.png" /></p>
          <p align="center"><img style="max-width: 100%" src="images/manuf2.png" /></p>
        </p>
        <p>
          Bob made the same documents for 12 Pizza with bacon frozen with the rest of direct labor cost 22.96.
        </p>
      </p>
      <p>* You have to make sure that you (your business activity) are subject to this method (product cost) according the law?</p>

    </section>

  </body>

</document>
