<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<document xmlns="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0"
  xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance"
  xsi:schemaLocation="http://maven.apache.org/XDOC/2.0 http://maven.apache.org/xsd/xdoc-2.0.xsd">

  <properties>
    <title>Beigesoft™ projects overview</title>
  </properties>

  <body>

    <!-- The body of the document contains a number of sections -->
    <section name="Beige-Software overview">

      <p><a href="https://www.facebook.com/Beigesoft-Accounting-All-In-One-401150900677249">Page on Facebook</a></p>

            
      <p>Keywords: Java open source software, free accounting software, Java reporting tools, PDF creator, Java PDF library, Jetty for Android, Java ORM library, JSP, JSTL, JSON, AJAX.</p>
      
      <h3>Products:</h3>

      <h4>Beigesoft™ Enterprise Information System.</h4>
      <p>This application never wastes your time because of:
        <p><b>It provides sufficient functionality:</b></p>
        <ul>
          <li>Double entry accounting system.</li>
          <li>General ledger, trial balance, balance sheet, stock items and other reports.</li>
          <li>It makes COGS FIFO/LIFO automatically for sales, sales returns, inventory losses.</li>
          <li>It makes sales tax (VAT, GST) automatically for sales, purchases and their returns.</li>
          <li>Sales tax (VAT, GST) methods: item/invoice basis, destination-based, aggregate rate, tax included in the price.</li>
          <li>Tracking payments for sales/purchases in national and foreign currencies.</li>
          <li>Payroll - automatic calculation of the taxes using withholding tax tables.</li>
          <li>Production - automatic calculation of the cost of a product from used materials, direct labor costs and other costs.</li>
          <li>Inventory - two dimensional (warehouse, place) registration, moving items inside warehouse, etc.</li>
          <li>Multi-databases (organizations) for standalone versions, which use SQlite database.</li>
          <li>Embedded Web-Store. Pricing - multicurrency, price depends on buyer's category, exporting price list to CSV</li>
          <li>and more.</li>
        </ul>
        * You can check its functionality by reading this documentation (without installation).
        <p><b>It's a reliable software:</b></p>
        <ul>
          <li>All its parts are under truly free licenses.</li>
          <li>It's open source software, so fixing an error or customizing is not a problem.</li>
          <li>It will never be downgraded or disappeared. You always can find it (binary and source code) in Central Maven Repository.</li>
          <li>This is a high performance software. The cloud version will never be slow even on weak computers.</li>
        </ul>
      </p>
      <p>This application requires Google Chrome, Opera or Chromium browser (html5-dialog ready).</p>
      <p><a href="privacypolicy-en.html">See Beigesoft™ EIS Privacy Policy.</a></p>
      <p><a href="beigekeys.html">See Beigesoft™ digital signatures.</a></p>
      <p>
        <a href="eis-bobs-pizza.html">See Beige EIS Bob's Pizza example.</a>
      </p>
      <p>
        Beigesoft™ EIS for MS Windows/Mac/*Nix <b>beige-accjet.bin.zip</b> and
        cloud version <b>beige-accweb.war</b> and other products
        you can find in central Maven repository <a href="https://search.maven.org/#search%7Cga%7C1%7Cg%3A%22org.beigesoft%22">https://search.maven.org/#search%7Cga%7C1%7Cg%3A%22org.beigesoft%22</a>
        or <a href="https://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/beigesoft/beige-accjet/">https://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/beigesoft/beige-accjet/</a>
      </p>
      <p>Beigesoft™ EIS for Android you can find in Google Play-Store (search "Beigesoft Enterprise Information System")
       or use link <a href="https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.beigesoft.accandr">https://play.google.com/store/apps/details?id=org.beigesoft.accandr</a></p>
      <p>
        Source code of Beigesoft™ EIS and other products you can find in <a href="https://github.com/demidenko05">https://github.com/demidenko05</a>
      </p>
      <p>
        Licenses:
        <ul>
          <li>BSD 2-Clause License - https://sites.google.com/site/beigesoftware/bsd2csl</li>
          <li>GNU General Public License version 2 - http://www.gnu.org/licenses/old-licenses/gpl-2.0.en.html</li>
          <li>The Eclipse Public License, Version 1.0 - http://www.eclipse.org/legal/epl-v10.html</li>
          <li>The Apache Software License, Version 2.0 - http://www.apache.org/licenses/LICENSE-2.0.txt</li>
          <li>CDDL + GPLv2 with classpath exception - https://javaee.github.io/glassfish/LICENSE</li>
          <li>MIT License - https://github.com/twbs/bootstrap/blob/master/LICENSE</li>
          <li>DejaVu fonts by Bitstream - https://dejavu-fonts.github.io/License.html</li>
          <li>SIL OPEN FONT LICENSE Version 1.1 - http://scripts.sil.org/cms/scripts/page.php?item_id=OFL_web</li>
        </ul>
      </p>

        <h4>Beigesoft™ PDF Writer.</h4>
              
        <p>This is light-weight (all JARs size is about 250KB), international friendly and fast PDF writer. This is actually reporting tool. It automatically makes pagination, tables (e.g. repeating header on every page).
         It's cross-platform writer - Standard Java and Android one.</p>
              
        <p>Benefits:</p>
        <ul>
          <li>It packs TTF font with only used characters. Asian languages (with hieroglyphs) TTF files are extremely huge.</li>
          <li>Ready for high load job. Performance test's (thread per invoice) results show that making 100 invoices (3pages each) takes less than 4 seconds on a regular notebook.</li>
          <li>There are not 3-d party libraries. Beigesoft™ Document Writer, Swing/Android graphics libraries, Logger are licensed under truly free GPLv2 and BSD 2-clause.</li>
        </ul>
        Although Beigesoft™ PDF Writer hasn't yet implemented graphic charts and other features, and it has no visual editor, it's really reliable to create complex black and white (including non-masked RGB images) business reports quickly.
        Visual editor is planned to be the same as MS Word or LibreOffice Writer. Here are PDF files for example:
        <a href="https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;pid=sites&amp;srcid=ZGVmYXVsdGRvbWFpbnxiZWlnZXNvZnR3YXJlfGd4OjM3YTU4MWFmNDNiYzZmYjk">Invoice sample</a> <a href="https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;pid=sites&amp;srcid=ZGVmYXVsdGRvbWFpbnxiZWlnZXNvZnR3YXJlfGd4OjNhZDczYWU4OWE2MDU3ODQ">Счет-фактура</a> <a href="https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;pid=sites&amp;srcid=ZGVmYXVsdGRvbWFpbnxiZWlnZXNvZnR3YXJlfGd4OjE4MTA3ODM1NTg3MTAyNzQ">Платежное поручение</a>
        <a href="https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;pid=sites&amp;srcid=ZGVmYXVsdGRvbWFpbnxiZWlnZXNvZnR3YXJlfGd4OmY1M2JjYjM4NTY2YTRlYw">Example of partially internationalized invoice with "VL-Gothic-Regular.ttf" (Japanese)</a>
        These sample reports clearly show abilities of this reporting tool. Source code that makes these reports is in <b>test</b> folder of the project's source.
      <h4>A-Jetty</h4>
      <p>A-Jetty is Jetty 9.2 adapted for Android, it can run precompiled JSP/JSTL. It works on Android Java as well as on standard Java 7+.</p>
      <p>
        JSP(plus JSTL) is the same WEB-view technology as ASPX, PHP and deprecated ASP. JSP and ASPX are faster than PHP and ASP, because of
        they are compiled into byte-code, which is executed (actually it's compiled on fly into CPU code) by Java VM or DOT.NET. PHP and ASP are script languages that is interpreted during runtime and it's never be compiled. Although there is PHP "fly compiler", but it's slower than Java or DOT-NET.
        All these technologies are used to build complex WEB-interface quickly.
      </p>
      <p>
        Using JSP(JSTL) allows you to create truly multi-platform WEB-applications cause A-Jetty can run them anywhere (on any operation system).
        The best way of using A-Jetty is using it as embedded server in a standalone WEB-application.
      </p>
      
      <h4>Beigesoft™ BLC (business logic common) and WEB libraries.</h4>
      <p>These libraries allow you to create cross-platform business application quickly. Beige-ORM is fast even on a smartphone. WEB-library automatically makes an entity's list and form to edit.
        Generated entity-picker already has pagination and filter. These libraries also include data replication via WEB-service (e.g. full database copy).
      </p>

      <h4>Beige-UML</h4>
<p>Beige-UML is a free, open source UML diagram editor. It has two user interfaces - standard desktop SWING one and Android one.</p>
<p>Features:</p>
  <ol>
    <li>It supports UML 2.4.1 compliant class diagram, package diagram, object diagram, sequence diagram and use case diagram.</li>
    <li>It generates UML class diagram from Java classes.</li>
    <li>It's a doclet that generates standard Javadoc with editable UML class diagrams.</li>
  </ol>
<p>This is the first free, truly cross-platform UML editor that can make a reliable (real-life) UML class diagram (with a frame, many classes and BUS-relationships). For non-huge projects generated Java-docs with PNG diagrams (with editable sources) is also reliable thing. Some customers demand this (that Beige-UML can do, but another free UML editors can't).
This is for programmers, so feel free to improve this project - add other diagrams, make Java-doc with SVG diagrams.
</p>
<p>This application you can download from <a href="https://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/beigesoft/beige-uml-swing/">https://repo1.maven.org/maven2/org/beigesoft/beige-uml-swing/</a>
  There <b>beige-uml-swing-[VERSION]-jar-with-dependencies.jar</b> is Swing application.
  Android version you can find in Google Play Store. Its source code you can download from <a href="https://github.com/demidenko05/beige-uml">https://github.com/demidenko05/beige-uml</a></p>
<p>Demo project <b>DemoUML.zip</b> and source of beige-android-demo (demo of Android tree/file-chooser, list-chooser etc.) you can find at <a href="http://sourceforge.net/projects/beigeuml/">http://sourceforge.net/projects/beigeuml/</a></p>
<p> <a href="https://sites.google.com/site/beigesoftware/gettingstartedgui">Beige UML getting started.</a> </p>
            
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
